<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book lang="en-US">
  <?ooogenerator OpenOffice.org/2.0$Linux OpenOffice.org_project/680m1$Build-8990?>

  <?oooversion ?>

  <bookinfo>
    <pubdate>Build date: @BUILD.DATE@</pubdate>

    <author>
      <firstname>François Tanguy, Didier Vojtisek</firstname>

      <firstname></firstname>
    </author>

    <title>Kermeta tutorial</title>

    <date>2006-09-25T10:35:34</date>

    <keywordset>
      <keyword>Kermeta</keyword>

      <keyword>metamodeling</keyword>

      <keyword>language</keyword>
    </keywordset>

    <subtitle>The FSM example</subtitle>

    <bibliomisc>Licence EPL</bibliomisc>

    <date>19/07/2006</date>

    <abstract>
      <para>This tutorial is part of a serie of tutorials that explain step by step one of the aspect of Kermeta. 
      This one is the master tutorial that will guide you through the different tutorials illustrating the 
      explanation using the Finite State Machine example.
      After having read this tutorial (and dependent tutorials) you will know how to create a metamodel, 
      add behavior and use it for simulation</para>
    </abstract>

    <publisher>
      <publishername>INRIA</publishername>

      <address>
        <state>France</state>
        <otheraddr>
          <ulink url="http://www.inria.fr">http://www.inria.fr</ulink>
        </otheraddr>
      </address>
    </publisher>

    <confgroup>
      <conftitle>title</conftitle>

      <confnum>Reference</confnum>

      <confsponsor>sponsor</confsponsor>
    </confgroup>
  </bookinfo>

  <preface>
    <?print-orientation portrait?>

    <title>Preface</title>

    <para><emphasis role="strong">Kermeta is a Domain Specific Language
    dedicated to metamodel engineering. It fills the gap let by MOF which
    defines only the structure of meta-models, by adding a way to specify
    static semantic (similar to OCL) and dynamic semantic (using operational
    semantic in the operation of the metamodel). </emphasis> <emphasis
    role="strong"> <emphasis role="strong">Kermeta uses the object-oriented
    paradigm like Java or Eiffel.</emphasis> </emphasis> <emphasis
    role="strong"> This document presents various aspects of the language,
    including the textual syntax, the metamodel (which can be viewed as the
    abstract syntax) and some more advanced features typically included in its
    framework. </emphasis></para>

    <important>
      <emphasis role="strong">Kermeta is an evolving software and d</emphasis>

      <emphasis role="strong">
        <emphasis role="strong">espite that we put a lot of attention to this
        document, it may contain errors (more likely in the code samples). If
        you find any error or have some information that improves this
        document, please send it to us using the bug tracker in the
        forge:</emphasis>
      </emphasis>

      <ulink type="" url="http://gforge.inria.fr/tracker/?group_id=32">
        <emphasis role="strong">
          <emphasis role="strong">
            <emphasis
            role="strong">http://gforge.inria.fr/tracker/?group_id=32</emphasis>
          </emphasis>
        </emphasis>
      </ulink>

      <emphasis role="strong">
        <emphasis role="strong">
          <emphasis role="strong" />
        </emphasis>
      </emphasis>

      <emphasis role="strong">
        <emphasis role="strong">
          <emphasis role="strong">or using the developer mailing list
          (kermeta-developers@lists.gforge.inria.fr)</emphasis>
        </emphasis>
      </emphasis>

      <emphasis role="strong">
        <emphasis role="strong">
          <emphasis role="strong" />
        </emphasis>
      </emphasis>

      Last check: v0.3.1
    </important>

    <tip>
      The most update version of this document is available on line from 

      <ulink type=""
      url="http://www.kermeta.org/">http://www.kermeta.org</ulink>

       .
    </tip>
  </preface>

  <chapter>
    <title>Prerequisites</title>

    <para></para>

    <caution>
      <para>KerMeta must be installed. If not, please read the "<ulink type=""
      url="../KerMeta-How-to-install-KerMeta/">How to install KerMeta</ulink>" tutorial.</para>
    </caution>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This tutorial has been written to give an overview of many concepts
    used through KerMeta project creation. Following this tutorial should give
    you the knowledge : to create KerMeta project to create KerMeta meta
    models to add behavior to KerMeta meta models to execute a model To cover
    all this features, we decided to start from an existing example. It is a
    reference you should browse each time you are in difficulty because it is
    a complete KerMeta project. This example is about the finite state machine
    which acronym is FSM. This tutorial is divided in several dependent
    sub-tutorials. So it means that the reader should follow the speech
    structure. Anyway, if you want to jump some sections, in each sub-tutorial
    you will find a section named "Prerequisites" which specify the minimal
    background needed to understand the contents. List of sub tutorials : How
    to create a KerMeta meta model How to add behavior to a KerMeta meta model
    How to run a FSM model and to use run configurations? Firstly, a section
    is dedicated to the finite state machine we want to model. The next
    section explains how to load files of the example in your Eclipse
    workspace. You will have access to every files. The last three sections
    point on one sub tutorial (in the list order above)</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Finite State Machine Specifications</title>

    <para>We want to represent IO/state machines. Inputs and outputs can be
    attached on each transition. To illustrate finite state machine, here is a
    simple example. This state machine recognizes the "hello!" motif and
    produces the "world!" motif. Here, we present this finite-state machine in
    a specific graphical syntax where states are represented as squares and
    transitions by arrow between squares. Input and outputs are present above
    transitions. Here, "h/w" says that we consume an "h" to produce a
    "w".</para>

    <figure>
      <title></title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="KerMeta-The-FSM-example_figures/helloWorldFSM.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>This simple state machine can be modeled and executed easily in
    Kermeta. See the following meta-model presented in a class diagram syntax.
    </para>

    <figure>
      <title></title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="KerMeta-The-FSM-example_figures/fsm-metamodel.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Loading the FSM example</title>

    <para></para>

    <caution>
      <para>The FSM example is available from Eclipse only if KerMeta is
      already installed.</para>
    </caution>

    <para>We start from the main Eclipse window.</para>

    <figure>
      <title></title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="KerMeta-The-FSM-example_figures/main_window.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Select : "File" &gt; "New"&gt;&gt; "Example..."&gt;&gt;&gt; A window
    appears. You are asked to choose a wizard for project creation. At the
    bottom of the list, you will find "Kermeta samples" item. Browse it and
    select "FSM Demo". The "Finish" button has been enabled. Click on
    it.</para>

    <figure>
      <title></title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="KerMeta-The-FSM-example_figures/wizard_selection.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Thanks to the wizard creation project, a project named
    "fr.irisa.triskell.kermeta.samples.fsm.demo" appeared on the left side of
    Eclipse.</para>

    <figure>
      <title></title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="KerMeta-The-FSM-example_figures/main_window_fsm_loaded.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>How to create a KerMeta meta model ?</title>

    <para>Please read <ulink type=""
      url="../KerMeta-How-to-create-a-metamodel/">"How to create a KermMeta meta model"</ulink> tutorial.</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>How to add behavior to a KerMeta meta model ?</title>

    <para>Please read <ulink type=""
      url="../KerMeta-How-to-add-behavior-to-a-metamodel/">how to add behavior to a metamodel</ulink>
    tutorial.</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>How to run a FSM model and to use run configurations?</title>

    <para>Please read <ulink type=""
      url="../KerMeta-How-to-use-run-configuration/">"How to use run configuration"</ulink> tutorial.</para>
  </chapter>
</book>