<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Textual editor for Kermeta users</title>

  <articleinfo>
    <date>Build date: @BUILD.DATE@</date>

    <author>
      <surname>François Tanguy</surname>
    </author>

    <date>09/01/2007</date>

    <keywordset>
      <keyword>Kermeta</keyword>

      <keyword>metemodelling</keyword>

      <keyword>language</keyword>
    </keywordset>

    <bibliomisc>Licence EPL</bibliomisc>

    <abstract>
      <para>This document is a presentation of the Kermeta textual editor for
      beginners.</para>
    </abstract>

    <publisher>
      <publishername>INRIA</publishername>

      <address><state>France</state><otheraddr><ulink url="???">
www.inria.fr</ulink></otheraddr></address>
    </publisher>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>The document</title>

    <para>Nowadays a textual editor is not just an editable document. Many
    informations have been provided to the user in order to get improved
    editing performances. It is quite common to find textual editor with
    coloring syntax, auto-completion and outline. These three items working
    together usually makes a good textual editor. That is the reason why the
    Kermeta platform provides such an editor. Below, you can find the global
    view of the Kermeta editor.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>The Kermeta Textual Editor</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="TextualEditorForKermetaUser_figures/textualEditor.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Auto-completion</title>

    <para>To develop faster and faster, some nice helpfull tools now are
    usual. One of them is the auto-completion. According to a context, a list
    of item will be proposed. Using the arrows key and the carriage return
    key, you can select quickly and easily the item you want. The important
    thing is that, the list of item is calculated in order to only propose
    some relevant items. The figure below shows the auto-completion for
    "stdio" which is a special class in Kermeta (as System for Java). The
    typed point makes the system think that you want to call a method on
    "stdio". Then all the callable methods are proposed and you can choose one
    of them.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Auto-Completion in the Kermeta Textual Editor</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="TextualEditorForKermetaUser_figures/autoCompletionSmall.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Outline</title>

    <para>The outline is a strucutral view of your program. Code is not
    visible in this view, but the structure that is to say packages, classes,
    attributes and methods are visible in a tree hierarchy. Usually the
    outline position is on the top right side of the Eclipse's window. You can
    get advantages of the outline, when your program reaches a big size and
    when it is difficult to get a good visibility on the program's strucutre.
    Browsing the outline is much more faster than browsing the file. Moreover,
    clicking on an item (packages, classes, attributes or methods) brings you
    to that item in the file.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>The outline in Kermeta Text Editor</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="TextualEditorForKermetaUser_figures/outlineSmall.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Errors reporting</title>

    <para>The textual editor is used to display extra pieces of information
    than simple text. In the figure below, a parsing error is reporting
    because of the semicolon which is not allowed in the language. The nice is
    thing is that in the Eclipse's problems view, just by double clicking on
    an error opens the errored file and make the cursor focusing on the
    correct line.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Error reporting</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="TextualEditorForKermetaUser_figures/errorReportingSmall.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Debugging information</title>

    <para>Kermeta is meant an executable language. So, we may want to debug
    programs because of their complexity. It is possible because Kermeta
    platform includes a debugger. Like in a Java style, some breakpoints can
    be added to the program by right clicking on the grey line at the left of
    the editor (as in the figure below). The breakpoint will be added in front
    the selected line. Afterwards, when running the debugger, the program will
    halt at every breakpoint it goes through. At this moment, you will be able
    to have a look at the variables' value and run step by step or step into
    some methods.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Debugging Information in the Kermeta Text Editor</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="TextualEditorForKermetaUser_figures/debuggingInformationSmall.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
</article>